Guide to the Stanford University Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University fiftieth anniversary celebration collection
1940-1941
SC0002
Stanford University
7.5 Linear feet
This collection includes minutes, budget records, correspondence, addresses, programs, clippings, and related records of the various committees and individuals involved with the 50th Anniversary Celebration. Correspondents include Ray Lyman Wilbur, Donald B. Tresidder, Morgan A. Gunst, and Frank F. Walker. Items of note include designs for a commemorative postage stamp, materials on the "Know Stanford" contest, radio script on the life of Leland Stanford, speech by Raymond Blaine Fosdick, and the address by Jackson E. Reynolds at the academic convocation of June 20, 1941.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, President's Office, 1965.
Information about Access
Open for research. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents note
This collection includes minutes, budget records, correspondence, addresses, programs, clippings, and related records of the various committees and individuals involved with the 50th Anniversary Celebration. Correspondents include Ray Lyman Wilbur, Donald B. Tresidder, Morgan A. Gunst, and Frank F. Walker. Items of note include designs for a commemorative postage stamp, materials on the "Know Stanford" contest, radio script on the life of Leland Stanford, speech by Raymond Blaine Fosdick, and the address by Jackson E. Reynolds at the academic convocation of June 20, 1941.
Access Terms
Davis, Paul H.; Fosdick, Raymond B., (Raymond Blaine), 1883-1972; Gunst, Morgan A.; Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace; Reynolds, Jackson E.; Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948
Collection Contents
- Fiftieth Anniversary materials, 1940-1941
  - Minutes of General Committee on Commemoration and the Executive Committee of the Committee on Commemoration of the 50th Anniversary of Stanford University (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - L.S.J.U. 50th Anniversary Revised Budget for Celebration of 50th Anniversary 10/31/40, and Expense Account February 1940--November 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - L.S.J.U. 50th Anniversary Revised Budget for Celebration of 50th Anniversary 10/31/40, and Expense Account February 1940--November 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 50th Anniversary [of the] University of Chicago, Publicity and Correspondence; Also 300th Anniversary of Harvard University (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 50th Anniversary [of the] University of Pennsylvania, Correspondence and Program (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Other Universities (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Universities--anniversaries (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Week of Commemoration--Delegates Institutions--Regrets (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Academic Week of Commemoration--Delegates Institutions Intending to Send Delegates but Who Failed To Do So (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Attendance at October Celebration; Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Address [sic.] For Various Occasions [one] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Committees (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "A" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Acknowledgements--Commemoration Week (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Address Publication (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "B" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Budget (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "C" (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Commencement 1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Commemoration--General (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "50th Anniversary Committee Organization--General" (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Palo Alto Committee (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Commemoration Dinner October 1, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Conferences and Conventions Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Congratulatory Messages (Excluding Those from Delegates) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cornerstone May 14, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "D" Incoming--Outgoing Correspondence--General (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Davis, Paul H. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Dedication of Hoover Library (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Delegate Mailings, etc. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Extra-Curricular Activities (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Departmental Exhibits, Reunions and Panels (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Exhibits (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Executive Secretary's Notes and Minutes--Contents Subdivided: Commemoration Committee/ Executive Committee/ Arrangements Committee/ Hoover Library Dedication/ Extra-Curricular Activities Committee/ Music Committee/ Pageantry Committee (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "No Titles"--Contain Copies of Press releases for 50th Anniversary (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - "F" (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Festival and Promenade--October 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Finance (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Finance (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Formal Exercises (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Formal Exercises--School Representatives (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Founder's Day (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "G" (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Committee on General Arrangements (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Guide Service (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Morgan A. Gunst Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "H" (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Hospitality (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Housing (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Humanities, Committee on (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "I" (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Information (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Inter--Office Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Institutions and Societies Invited to Celebration (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Invitations--General (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "J" (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "K" (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Know Stanford" Contest (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "L" (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "M" (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Mailing List (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mailings (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Mimeograph and Printed Material (Forms, Tickets, Programs, Memos, etc.) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous minutes (Planning Sept. 12, 1939 and Institute and Seminars 1940) (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Memorial Church Service October 5 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Motion Pictures (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Music (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Mc" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Collegiate Aviation Meet--1941 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "N" (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - News Bulletin (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - News Releases--General (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "O" (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Offers of Assistance (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Opening Exercises October 1 Celebration (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Office Operation (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Committee of 125 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "P" (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Committee of Pageantry (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Panel: "Future Aims of the Nations" etc. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - General Committee on Pageantry Music and Exhibits (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Personnel (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, correspondence regarding (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Postage Stamp--Commemorative of 50th Anniversary (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - President's Luncheon June 20, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - President's Luncheon October 3, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Publicity Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 50th Anniversary Celebration Program (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 50th Anniversary Celebration Publicity (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Q" (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "R" (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Radio Broadcast--Board of Trustee's Meeting (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Radio Script Life of Leland Stanford (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Radio--General (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Reunions--Fraternities, Clubs (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Rose Bowl Activities (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Southern Pacific (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "S" (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Statistics (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Suggestions (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Student Committee (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Symposium Dinner June 18 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Suggestions for Symposium and Conferences (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Committee on Symposium and Conferences; Includes Symposium Program (1 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Symposium Speakers (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Symposium Speeches--Originals (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "T" (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Tressider Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "U" (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "V" (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "W" (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Mr. Walker Correspondence--General (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Wilbur Correspondence--General (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Commemorative Week "Tickets, Program, etc." (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - 50th Anniversary Register (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Commemorative Committee News Bulletin--Miscellaneous Pieces (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 50th Anniversary--9th Stanford Alumni Conference February 8-9, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 50th Anniversary Luncheon--San Francisco Chamber of Commerce May 14, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 50th Anniversary Commemoration Week Symposium June 16-19 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 50th Anniversary Hoover Library Dedication June 20, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 50th Anniversary Commemoration week Academic Convocation June 20, 1941, Jackson E. Reynolds Address (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 50th Anniversary Birthday--Commemoration Week October 1-5, 1941; Miscellaneous Programs; Stanford Players ‘Thunder Rock" October 1st Banquet--Raymond B. Fosdick "Let The Winds of Freedom Blow" (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 50th Anniversary Birthday Commemoration--October 1-5, 1941; Festival and Promenade October 3; Memorial Church Service--October 5 (Including F.M> McFarland's Address); All Woman's Luncheon October 2; Programs of Discussion (With Ticket) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 50th Anniversary Commemoration Week, June 6-21; Unveiling of Wilber Portrait; Exhibits, Form Letters, San Francisco Symphony Concert June 20; Roy Harris "Ode to Truth" Commissioned for 50th Anniversary and Played March 9, Founder's Day; Invitation to 50th Anniversary (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 50th Anniversary Associates Plan (Not Used?) (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - 50th Anniversary Clippings Palo Alto Times and Stanford Daily Anniversary Issues (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - 50th Anniversary List of Letters in Bond Volumes (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "The University and the Future of America" Book; Stanford University Press, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - 50th Anniversary Edition; Palo Alto Times, 1941 Mar 7 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - San Jose Mercury News--Diamond Jubilee for Stanford University (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1941 Reproduction of San Jose Daily Mercury front page for Oct. 2, 1891 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 50th Anniversary Greetings and Congratulations from Various Universities: volume 1 A-J, volume 2 K-Z (Box 13)
  - Bound version of Reynolds' convocation address "New Paths and Old" (Box 13)
  - 50th Anniversary Edition; Palo Alto Times, 1941 Mar 7 (Box 14)
- Additional Materials, 1940-1941
  Materials were previously classified in the Stanford University Publications and Ephemera Collection "4digit" collection.
  - Various Fiftieth Anniversary materials (Box 1)